and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5. The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is never
the less haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into break free of
the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this
spiritual reality like. How do we engage?
with it well. How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian
priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live
Colin show focused on enchantment in creation the union of the scene and
unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the
Lord of Spirits.
I don't know what intro may or may not have been inserted before I began, but welcome
to the list.
So this is a very special episode which is being recorded for all those folks who aren't
going to be at the Lord of Spirits Conference this week, at which we're recording this week's
actual episode.
But what you won't get to hear live, because the internet at the Adiokian Village is
lame. So you'll have to hear it recorded after the fact. But those of you who are not in attendance,
we'll get to hear this first. So this is sort of the consolation prize, the turtle wax as it were
of Lord of Spirits episodes. And so since unfortunately, those of you who are listening to this when it first
airs on Thursday evening are going to be missing out on whatever sort of party is happening at the
village. I thought I would talk a little bit about ways in which one might
miss out on a party in the Second Millennium BC in Mesopotamia. There are
several ways you could do this, right? So one way is you could not have proper
clothing for the party or just your clothing isn't clean. And this could
especially happen to you if you're kind of a Karen.
And so when you take your clothing to the cleaners,
you do something like is recorded on this ancient
Acadian tablet.
Come now, cleaner.
Let me give you a commission.
Clean my clothes.
Don't neglect the commission I am giving you.
Don't do what you usually would.
You should lay flat the fringe in the border.
You should stitch the front to the inside.
You should pick out the thread of the border. You should soak the thin part in a stew. You should strain that with a strainer.
You should open out the fringes. You should wash it with clean water. You should treat it as if it were important cloth.
Will this be ready overnight? Will this be in a closed container? You should use soap and mix in gypsum. You should beat it on a stone.
known, you should stir it in a crock and rinse it. You may want to stretch.
it out and comb it. You should tap it with a corn eltrie branch. You should fluff out the flattened
nap. You should work the woven work with a pin. You should split the seam and cool it. You should
dry it in the cool of the evening. If the south wind does not dry it, you should put it on a rack
in the east wind. Make sure it's cool. Carry this out. I'll make you very happy fast. You should
to deliver it to my home, a measure of barley will be poured into your lap.
cleaner answers him by a Lord of the wash tub who keeps me alive, lay off. Nobody but a
creditor or a tax collector would have the gall to talk the way you do. Nor could anyone's
hands do the job. What you ordered me I could not narrate, declaim, speak, or repeat. Come now,
upstream of town at the city's edge, let me show you a place to launder this big job you have on
your hands you can set to yourself. Don't miss your chance.
Seize the day. Do ease if you
please the countless tangles of a cleaner. If you can't give yourself more
breathing room, the cleaner is not yet born who will pay you any mind.
They'll think you and Ninny, so as they say, you'll get all heated up and then
you'll have a stroke. So see, your liable to get told off, made to do your own
laundry, miss the party. Another thing that could happen could leave you left out of
of the party and the second millennium BC.
has to do with having a kid. Everybody loves their kids. People who adopt love their adopted kids
as much as a biological kid. Even if that kid's a little weird, right? You'll love that kid. You
want to protect that kid. There's just such a story written in Kuneiform on the bottom of a
a monkey's foot down in Mesopotamia.
Miss and Hoody Romani, slave woman of Miss Karebru, the palace woman of Assa Eden, who lifted
Nero-Ariba, the monkey man out of the river, has raised him.
He is her son.
Whoever shall bring a lawsuit or complaint concerning him, he shall give up six sons and let him
go free.
And accordance with the command of the gods, they must not monkey with the
monkey. So see if you have a monkey child who you've adopted and raised as your own,
gotta be careful about bringing him to parties. You might get thrown out.
Even in a party where kids are allowed, bringing your adopted monkey child might be a problem.
Finally, everybody wants to be the life of the party. Everybody wants to have that little
crowd gather
around them and be waiting on their every word. One way to do that is to be funny, to
be humorous at a party. But telling jokes can go wrong, right? Very easy to cross lines
and offend. And let me suggest we have this is actually from the early first millennium
BC and Mesopotamia. We have a very early stand-up set.
for a professional jester. And I don't know how these jokes would go over.
The lion can terrify, I can let out air too. The lion can switch his tail, I can
wag my tail too. I'm as trustworthy as a sieve. I hold onto my followers like a net.
I sing like a she-ass. Thaft is important to me. Whatever I see doesn't stay
where it was.
I've gotten large from starvation, enormous for meeting.
I make myself throw up ten quarts I feast on thirty more.
I don't leave off till I fill the bushel to the brim.
Among the shortest of them, the tallest of them.
There's none like me among women.
My limbs are elephant-ine, my face are hyenas.
I tower like a tortoise, I cannot be equaled.
even if I
weren't alive, how much would my lover be loving me? He would keep turning around
forward and backward like a trained crab. He can't hurt a U in the 20 acre field.
By the city gate on account of me and my rats, I used up all my plans.
Jester, what can you do? Rope weaving and singing laments, squeezing out fruit juice and brewing
beer.
What can you do? Snatching on the run, podweeds and turnips,
Grotes and stink ward or anything else?
Jester, what can you do of the whole exorcist's craft?
Nothing's beyond me. Jester, how do you exercise?
Here's how. I take over the haunted house. I set up the holy water. I tie up the goat.
I skin a donkey and stuff it with straw. I tie a bundle of reeds, set it on fire and toss it inside.
I
I spared the boundaries of the house and its surroundings, but the haunt of the house,
the serpent, the scorpion are not spared.
In October, what is your diet?
Thou shalt dine on spoiled oil and onions and goose pluckings in porridge.
In November, what is your diet?
Thou shalt dine on podweed and turnips and cleanser plant in crow foot.
In December, what is your diet?
I shall die on wild donkey dung in bitter garland.
and Enmerchaff and sour milk.
In January, what is your diet?
Now shall dine on goose eggs and dung, embedded in sand,
and cumin infused with Euphrates water and ghee.
If February, what is your diet?
Now shall dine on hot bread and donkeys,
rear end, stuffed with dog turds and fly dirt.
So I don't know if any of those classic bits.
from 3,000 years ago had you rolling in the aisles.
Or if any of those comedy stylings of the ancient areas
made up for not being able to go to the Lord of Swerves Conference
but hey, it's better than nothing.
The crucifixion and resurrection of Christ are central events in our salvation.
Yet few Christians have a good grasp of the first